Guide to the Ray Lyman Wilbur Personal Papers SC0064B
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Ray Lyman Wilbur personal papers
1829-1949
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman)
SC0064B
166.5 Linear Feet
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Ray Lyman Wilbur graduated from Stanford University (B.S. 1896, M.S. 1897) and from Cooper Medical College (M.D. 1899). He served as lecturer and professor of physiology and of medicine (1897-1903), Dean of the Cooper Medical College (Stanford) (1911-1916), third President of Stanford University (1916-1943), Chancellor of Stanford, and Secretary of the Interior (September 1929-1933) under President Hoover.
Scope and Contents note
Collection includes correspondence; scrapbooks; publications; speeches and trip notes; rough draft of Wilbur's "Memoirs"; R. L. Wilbur's will; honorary degrees; letters from Marguerite Blake Wilbur (Mrs. R. L. Wilbur) to her children, some of which are titled ("Doings"); and files on associations with which Wilbur was involved, friends and associates, clubs to which he belonged, conferences, and issues such as environmental protection, civil defense during World Wars I and II, prohibition, and anti-vivisection. Among the correspondents are Herbert Hoover, Northcutt Ely, Robert Eckles Swain, and Timothy Hopkins. Papers also include Wilbur family correspondence (1829-1949).
Separated Material
The Bulletin, Extra Edition (Death of President Harding) 1923 Aug 3
San Francisco Journal Death of President Harding) 1923 Aug 3
San Francisco Chronicle (Death of President Harding) 1923 Aug 3
San Francisco Examiner (Death of President Harding) 1923 Aug 3
San Francisco Examiner (Funeral for President Harding) 1923 Aug 4
San Francisco Examiner (Funeral for President Harding) 1923 Aug 5
The Bulletin (President Harding's Funeral) 1923 Aug 10
Philadelphia Public Ledger (Special edition on US Presidents) 1925 Mar 1
New York Times (Honoring Lindbergh) 1927 June 5
New York Times (Honoring Lindbergh) 1927 Jun 12
San Francisco Chronicle (Hoover Presidential Inauguration) 1929 Mar 5
San Francisco News (Coolidge's death) 1933 Jan 5
San Francisco Chronicle (Coolidge's death) 1933 Jan 6
San Francisco Examiner (Coolidge's death) 1933 Jan 6
The Call Bulletin (Coolidge's death) 1933 Jan 5
Palo Alto Times (Fiftieth Anniversary of Stanford University) 1941 Mar 7
New York Times (Kennedy Shot in Dallas) 1963 Nov 23
San Francisco Examiner (Death of Roosevelt) 1945 Apr 13
San Francisco Chronicle (FDR dies) 1945 Apr 13
Publications Index
European Sanitation Observations 1904
Report on an Epidemic of Diphtheria 1904
Routine Treatment and Complications of Typhoid Fever 1905
An Unusual Case of Antitoxin Rash 1906
Some Points on the Symptoms and Localization of Intestinal Carcinomata, with Report on Four Cases 1908
Department of Medicine, Stanford University 1911
Abnormal Body Temperatures in Injuries of the Cervical Spinal Cord 1911
Some Relations of the Nervous Mechanism of the Heart to Drug Effects, as Indicated by experiments on the Terrapin 1911
The Significance of Pelvic Pain 1911
Should There be Two Degrees in Medicine? 1911
Some Glimpses of Dr. Jordan 1911
Urobilin: Its Clinical Significance 1912
Early Diagnosis of Epidemic Poliomyelitis 1912
The Teaching of Therapeutics 1913
The Physician of the Future 1913
A Charity with No Evil Features 1913
Medical Inspections of the Industries-National, State, Municipal, or Private 1914
The Therapeusis of Pericarditis 1914
Surgery of Peptic Ulcer 1914
Medicine as a Vocation 1914
Early Symptomatology of Subacute Bacterial Endocarditis 1914
Leukemia-an Infection? 1915
The Education of the Physician 1915
The Public Health Question in San Francisco 1915
Address to the Graduating Class of Nurses from the Training School of the San Francisco Hospital 1915
Medical Inspection of the Industries 1915
Expectations from Student Self Government 1916
The University and Social Service 1916
President Wilbur's Address to Graduates 1916
The University and the American Spirit 1916
Research 1916
Remarks of President Ray Lyman Wilbur at Vocational Guidance Assembly 1917
Anti-vivisection 1917
Duty of Americans in Present Crisis 1917
Research and its Applications 1917
The Look Ahead 1917
Inescapable Responsibility 1917
A Faculty Viewpoint 1917
Address to the Graduates 1917
Letter to Miss Addie Wright 1917
Stanford Mena and the War 1917
Food and the War 1917
Transactions and Proceedings of the National Association of State Universities 1917
Memoirs of Benvenuto Cellini 1918
The Response of the American People to the Messages and Policies of Mrs. Hoover 1918
Theodore Roosevelt 1919
War Problems and Food 1918
Fighting with Food 1918
The Relation of the Hospital to the Community 1918
Commencement Address 1918
Food in the War Today 1918
Social Insurance 1918
Food Conservation for World Relief 1918
United States Food Administration 1918
The Standpoint of the Physician 1919
Success 1919
Russia, Our Neighbor 1919
American Citizenship, the World Ideal 1919
Letter to Blauer, Miss Emma 1919
Address to Graduating Class 1919
Letter to Kane, Thomas F. 1919
The Needs of Stanford 1919
League of Nations 1919
Letter to Stevenson, A. E. 1919
Letter to Daniels, A. H. 1919
The Opportunity of the American Woman 1919
Hoover, Herbert-A Personal Sketch 1920
Stanford and Medicine 1920
Foreword 1920
Letter to Barnes, Julius H. 1920
Address to Graduating Class 1920
America's Opportunity 1920
The Problems of the Endowed University 1920
Letter to Bryan, Sam 1920
Limitations of Students: A Problem 1920
Letter to Allen, Charles S. 1921
Address to San Francisco Conference of Secondary and Normal Schools 1921
Letter to Keesling, Francis V. 1921
Letter to Orth, Charles D. 1921
Stanford's Progress is Measured 1921
Public Health 1921
Recreation and Health 1921
The Relation of the Church to Public Health 1921
Medicine-A Look Ahead 1922
The University of the Future-A Recruiting and Training Center for the Public Health Professionals 1922
Remarks on the Gifted Student 1922
Letter to Considine, John 1922
Letter to Goodrich, Leroy R. 1922
Universities Helping to Solve Industrial Problems of Industrial Relations 1922
Report on Undergraduate Medical Curriculums: What Subjects, if any, Should be Transferred to the Graduate Medical School? 1922
Medical Education of Present and Near Future 1922
Educational Standards in Physiotherapy 1922
Address to the Conference on Educational Research and Guidance 1922
Stanford of the Past and the Present 1922
Address to Graduating Class 1922
Public Health and Human Welfare vs. Mosquito 1922
Animal Experimentation vs. Antivivisection 1923
Antivivisection and Popular Legislation-Practical Observation 1923
Letter to Work, Hubert 1923
Address to the Graduating Class 1923
Human Welfare and Modern Medicine 1923
El progreso del genero humane y la medicina moderna: Discurso presidencial 1923
The Advantages of Distribution of Research Funds to Universities Rather than to Independent Research Institutions 1923
The Doctor's Service to Humanity 1923
Yes, Better Health is Due to the Doctors 1923
Periodical Physical Examinations 1923
Progress of Medicine and Surgery since 1901 1923
Religion and Man as a Social Animal 1924
Why We Have Schools 1924
Statement to the California Journal 1924
Address to the Academy of Medicine of Cincinnati 1923
Why Have a Periodical Examination? 1924
The Eclipse of Magic in Medicine 1924
Address before the House of Delegates of the American Medical Association 1924
Address to Graduating Class 1924
The New Public Health 1924
Objectives of Public School Education 1924
Maintaining Standards Without Excessive Standardization 1924
Public Health Preventive Medicine and Scientific Progress are Analyzed by Wilbur, Dr. Ray Lyman 1924
Stanford University 1925
Intelligence First 1925
The New Public Health 1925
American Republic Indebted to Washington's Intelligence 1925
Voluntary Management of Community Problems 1925
The Future Practitioner 1925
Address to the Students of the University of Illinois College of Medicine 1925
The Place for the Western University 1925
Address to Graduating Class "Blinders" (under Publications-"A-C") 1925
Religion's Allies Towards the New Day 1925
Fraternity Chapters 1925
Letter to San Francisco Examiner 1925
The Institute of Pacific Relations 1926
Address at Speakers Dinner, Community Chest 1926
The Community Chest 1926
Health as a Business Asset 1926
The Junior College: A Message 1926
Address to the Stanford Conference on Business Education 1926
Stanford's Limitation of Students 1926
President Wilbur Outlines the Future 1926
Saving Time in the Medical School 1926
Address Given at Laying of the 1926 Class P1ate 1926
Address to Graduating Class 1926
Eugenics and Public Health 1926
Public Health Situation in California 1926
The Lag in the Health Program 1926
The Good Old Days are Gone -- Forever! 1926
Knowing How and Why 1926
What's Education For? 1926
Mutual Understanding in the Pacific 1926
Further Limitations of the Lower Division 1926
The Future Program of Stanford 1927
Memorandum 1927
Altering the Medical Curriculum 1927
Address to the Graduating Class 1927
An Interpretation of America in Pacific Relations 1927
The Position of the Institute 1927
The Honor System in Medical Practice 1927
An Adventure in Friendship 1927
Progress in Higher Education in the United States 1927
Statement for the San Diego Tribune 1927
The Cost of Medical Care 1928
Shadow Diplomacy Passing 1928
Herbert Hoover 1928
Interview for Stanford Daily 1928
Review of The Restless Pacific 1928
To the Alumni 1928
The Conference Method in International Relations 1928
Stanford Is All Right 1928
The Sixth Pan American Conference 1928
Medical Progress in an Economic World 1928
Stanford Is All Right 1928
Address to Graduating Class 1928
The Committee on the Cost of Medical Care 1928
1928 "Quad" Dedicated to Hoover, Herbert 1928
The Cost of Medical Care 1928
Address to New Students, for Stanford Daily 1928
Statement on the value of Public Health Nursing to the Nurse 1928
Statement sent to National Organization for Public Health Nursing 1928
Hoover—the Beloved Chief 1928
Address on Matriculation Sunday, Stanford University 1928
The New Day: Campaign Speeches of Hoover, Herbert, Introduction to 1928
The Havana Conference of 1928 1928
The New Childhood 1928
Greetings to the Members of the California Scholastic Press Association 1928-1929
The Cost of Medical Care 1928-1929
Stanford Handbook 1928-1929
President-Elect Hoover 1929
United States Veterans Bureau Medical Bulletin 1929
The Relationship of Medical Education to the Cost of Medical Care 1929
Message to 1929 Stanford Quad 1929
Contributions of the Laboratory to the Progress of Civilization 1929
Hoover Overseas and War Service Organizations 1929
Science in the Government 1929
Blinders for Youth 1929
Address at the Inauguration of the President of the University of New Mexico 1929
Radio Speech 1929
Talk at Red Cross 1929
The Relationship of Medical Education to the Cost of Medical Care 1929
Local Self Government in Education 1929
The American Home in Citizenship Training 1929
"Shifting Standards of Student Conduct" Address to Eleventh Annual Conference of the National Association of Dear and Advisors 1929
Remarks before the Radio Education Conference 1929
Wayside Improvements 1929
The Laboratory in Civilization 1929
Pioneers of Today 1929
Uncle Sam Has a New Indian Policy 1929
Remarks at the opening of the Conference on Oil Conservation 1929
The Future of the Public Domain 1929
National Parks-An American Institution 1929
Tackling a Huge Construction Problem 1929
Address before the American Dental Association 1929
Taming Wild Oil Wells 1929
Medicine in Service 1929
The Place of the Fraternity in the Future University 1929
Address in connection with the Washington Tuberculosis Seal Sale 1929
What About Our Public Lands 1929
Statement to the Committee on expenditures in the Executive Departments 1929
The Committee on the Cost of Medical Care 1930
Talk in connection with the Meeting of National Student Federation of the United States 1930
Speech in behalf of the Voters' Service of the National League of Women Voters 1930
Children in a Modern World 1930
The Anticipation of Future Needs 1930
Address at the Twentieth Anniversary Dinner of the Boy Scouts of America 1930
Address at the conference of Liberal Arts Colleges 1930
Flexible Standards 1930
The First Three Years' Work of the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care and Its Plans for the Future 1930
Facts to Face the Future: The Task of the Committee on the Cost of Medical Care 1930
The Educational Mill 1930
Better Homes in America 1930
Address before the American Child Health Association Conference for the State May Day Chairmen 1930
Our Test Tube Civilization 1930
Address Made on the Collier's Radio Hour 1930
Better Homes Week Programs in 6500 Communities 1930
Education and Health, a Community Problem 1930
The Advancing Profession 1930
Some Aspects of the World Movement for Mental Health 1930
Man, the Experimenter 1930
The Forward Advance of Medicine 1930
Address to the Conference of State and Provincial Health Authorities of North America 1930
Higher and Higher Education 1930
Address before the Committee on Recreation and Physical Education of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection 1930
Speech in connection with the International Good-will Program for the American School of the Air 1930
Address at the National Oratorical Contest 1930
Memorandum-Warburg Testimonial Meeting 1930
Government, Industry, and Conservation 1930
A Nation Looks at Its Children 1930
Speech Naming Hoover Dam 1930
Evening Talk at Las Vegas, Nevada 1930
The White House Conference and the Rural Child 1930
Continental Conservation 1930
The Role of Education in the Advancement of Mankind 1930
Radio Address 1930
Speech in the National Radio Forum 1930
Address in connection with the Negro Education Program of American Education Week 1930
A Survey and a Challenge 1930
Tomorrow the Child Will Be King 1930
Address at the National Pioneer Dinner of the Oregon Trail Memorial Association (A Tribute to the Western Pioneers by All the States of the Union), on the 100th Anniversary of the Birth of Egra Meeker 1930
Finding of the President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership 1931
Salvaging the Small Colleges 1931
Address before the Governors Conference on Oil 1931
Der Fortschritt der Menscheit durch Bildung 1931
Address delivered at the National Education Association Building 1931
Address at the Special Convocation at Gallaudet College 1931
Damning the Oil Flood 1931
Address to the Trustees of the Lincoln Memorial University 1931
Mental Health as a National Problem 1931
Illiteracy 1931
Holidays with the President 1931
The Indian Today 1931
Speech to the Military Order of the World War 1931
The Health Officer as an Educator 1931
Your Child's Health 1931
Two Years of the Department of the Interior 1929-1931
Address at the Dedication of the Institute of Human Relations, Yale University 1931
A Philosophy of American Education 1931
The Radio in Our Republic 1931
A New Day for the Indian 1931
A Progress Report at the Department of the Interior 1931
Address at the Smith Vocational Training High School 1931
Slide Rule Civilization 1931
Commencement Address at the New York University 1931
Moulding Men 1931
Unshackled Universities 1931
Let's Be Health 1931
Address at the Dedication of Lassen National Volcanic Park 1931
Health Instruction the Best Social Insurance 1931
Dedication of the Colonial National Monument 1931
Address in connection with the Chicago Regional Conference of the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection 1931
Speech in connection with the Wingate Athletic Club 1931
Speech Accepting Deeds to Lands in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park 1931
Some Educational Blue Prints 1931
The Hope of the Children's Charter 1931
The Widening Functions of the Teacher 1931
Jordan, David Starr 1931
As I Know Hoover, Herbert 1931
Let Us Provide Better Homes 1931
The Role of the Hospital in the Sphere of Health 1931
Speech before the Young Republicans of New Jersey 1931
Speech in connection with the Community Chest Drive 1931
Keeping the Doctor Up to Date 1931
Self-Management, the Basis of Citizenship 1931
Speech at the National Republican Club 1931
The Fundamental Place of the Hospital in the Practice of Medicine 1931
Talk before the Board of Consultants on School Finances 1931
Washington as Pioneer 1931
Making Democracy Safe 1931
Knowing How and Why 1932
The Economics of Public Health and Medical Care 1932
The Cost of Medical Care 1932
Address at the District of Columbia Dental Society 1932
Statement before a Sub-committee of the Senate Committee on the Judiciary 1932
Child Conference Results 1932
One Step Forward 1932
Address to the Conference of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People 1932
May Day-National Child Health day 1932
Nutrition 1932
Address in connection with the formal transfer the United States of the Birthplace of George Washington and the burial place of his ancestors 1932
Children in National Emergencies 1932
Rounding out the School Program 1932
Address in connection the services of the Military Order of the World War 1932
The Fundamental Place of the Hospital in Practice of Medicine 1932
Choosing a Job in 1732 vs. Choosing a Job in 1932 1932
National Parks in the East 1932
Why a White House Conference? 1932
Our Democracy at the Crossroads 1932
Is Democracy Safe? 1932
Address to the American Association of State Highway Officials 1932
Address in connection with the Community Chest Drive 1932
The High Points in the REcommendations of the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care 1932
Medicine-A Pace-maker for Civilization 1932
The Final Report of the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care 1932
Better Homes and Better Nation 1932
Science Guide the Department of the Interior 1932
Camping and Education 1932
Cubberly: His Significance to Stanford University 1932
Address on University Development of Work in the Social Sciences 1932
The Role of the Hospital in the Sphere of Health 1932
Medicine at the Crossroads 1933
Is This a New Renaissance 1933
The Middle Class and Medical Costs 1933
Stanford Aid for Students 1933
Public Education Moves Up 1933
The Conquest of Illness 1933
Foreword in America's Little House 1934
What is a University? 1934
Medicine in Community Service 1934
Community Nursing Needs 1934
Educational Aspects of Radiology 1934
Review of the Accomplishments of the council on Medical Education and Hospitals 1934
Provision of Adequate Medical Care 1934
University Training in Citizenship 1934
Cherish our children 1934
Some Points on Blue Print Medical Education 1934
What Did Mr. Hoover Do? 1934
Help for the Deafened 1934
Talk at the Opening Assembly, Stanford University 1934
Talk at Matriculation Sunday services 1934
Message for the New Year's edition of the Japanese-American Courier 1934
The Children's Charter 1934
Inspection of Medical Schools and Survey of Medical Education 1934
Review of Challenge to Liberty 1934
Educations Future Contribution to Health 1934
The Doctor's Part in Medical Care 1934
Medicine 1934
Art in an American City 1934
The Prolongation of Life 1934
Report of the council on Medical Education and Hospitals 1935
University Men in a Practical World 1935
Flock Flying 1935
Greeting to Stanford Daily 1935
Biology in the University of Tomorrow 1935
Where is Stanford Going? 1935
Talk at the Mark Twain Centennial Dinner, Bohemian Club 1935
Speech at College of Physicians and Surgeons 1935
Post-Doctoral Training for Productive Scholarship 1935
Hopkins, Timothy—Stanford Man 1936
Education Never Stops for the Doctor 1936
Report of the Council on Medical Education and Hospitals 1936
Speech to the American Provident Society 1936
Saving as an Individual Responsibility 1936
Address at the Dedication of the Stanford Memorial Hall 1936
Keep Your Trail Clean 1936
Man: A Saving Animal 1936
Talk at Opening Assembly, Stanford University 1936
Forward to Stanford University-A History of Twenty Five Years 1936
Talk on Matriculation Sunday 1936
Institute of Pacific Relations 1937
People Need Desire to Understand to Take Advantage of Inventions 1937
Statement for the San Diego Russ 1937
Leadership in Medical Education 1937
The King of Killers 1937
Who Should Select America's Movies 1937
Coasting 1937
Final Words to Graduating Classes 1937
The Health Status and Health Education of Negroes: A Critical Summary 1937
Leadership in Medical Education 1937
Statement to Palo Alto Times 1937
Talk at the Dedication of the Timothy Hopkins Room in the Stanford University Libraries 1937
Self-Management or Choices 1937
The Significance of the Junior College with Particular Reference to Awarding the Bachelor's Degree at the end of the Sophomore Year 1937
Talk to the Conference of social Hygiene Executives 1937
Statement in A.R.A. Association Review 1937
Tribute to Lanagan, James Francis 1937
Camp Cooking 1937
Stanford University 1937
The March of Medicine 1938
The Health Status of Negroes in the United States 1938
Critique of a Congress 1938
Greeting to the California Newspaper Publishers Association Meeting 1938
The Old Guard and the New Recruit 1938
Report of the Chairman of the Council on Medical Education and Hospitals of the American Medical Association 1938
Message to The Key Reporter 1938
Guest Editorial in Student Life 1938
Statement for the Stanford Medical Alumni Bulletin 1938
Statement for the Louisville, Kentucky Courier Journal 1938
Report of Council on Medical Education and Hospitals 1938
Medicals School, Internships, and Advancing standards in the Specialities 1938
The Strategic Position of the Red Cross in Relation to Public Health Safety 1938
Kellogg, Vernon Lyman, Scientist 1938
Pacific House: The Theme Building of the Golden Gate International Exposition 1938
Statement regarding Christmas Seal Campaign 1938
The Commonwealth Club and California's Future 1938
Comment on an article by Jones, Mark M. on "Has Education Let Business Down?", in Nation's Business 1938
Blind Spots 1938
International Expositions as Factors for Peace 1938
Laboratory of Democracy 1938
McDowell, John Eara 1938
Choice 1938
The Hospitals' Part in Medical Education 1938
Letter to New Students in Stanford Daily 1938
Address at Stanford University Assembly 1938
Economic Illiteracy 1938
My Word to Freshman 1938
Letter to College Years 1938
Education Appeals for Humanity 1938
Message for Big Game Issue of The Stanford Daily 1938
Foreword for booklet on New Building of the School of Education at Stanford 1938
Comments sent to the editor of The Forum 1938
What is a University? 1939
The Pacific Area Golden Gate International Exposition 1939
Statement Relative to the Anti-Semitism Movement 1938
Letter for Motion Picture Research Council News-Bulletin 1938
What America Owes Me 1939
What I Owe America 1939
Grandfather vs. Grandson in America Today 1939
Stanford University 1939
Remarks on Learning for Living Radio Program 1939
Statement to Palo Alto Times regarding Stanford Alumni Conference 1939
Culture of the Pacific 1939
The Protection of the Public through the activities of the Council on Medical Education and Hospitals of the American Medical Association 1939
Discussion of Odum, Howard, W's Paper, "The South as Testing Ground for the Regional Approach to Public Health and Welfare" 1939
Three Appreciations of Pius XI 1939
Social Hygiene-A Task of All the People 1939
Preparing the Child for Citizenship 1939
Radio's Responsibility 1939
Notes relative to retiring Stanford University professors 1939
California as a Home for Private Schools 1939
Address to the Meeting of the American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business 1939